Look, I hope you're excited.
興奮してるかな？
You really should be.
そうあるべきだ｡
You've been through 80% of the course and it's all been building up to this moment.
コースの8割を消化し､ この瞬間まですべてが積み重なってきた｡
Today you will be training your own proprietary LLM for for fun and for profit.
今日､ あなたは楽しみながら､ そして利益を得るために､ 独自のLLMをトレーニングすることになる｡
It all starts here.
すべてはここから始まる｡
So what is actually involved in today?
では､ 今日は実際に何があるのか？
We're going to start with some stuff that maybe isn't so thrilling.
まずは､ あまりスリリングではないものから始めよう｡
We're going to talk hyperparameters one more time.
ハイパーパラメーターについて､ もう1度話そう｡
I've got some essential hyperparameters to go through with you.
必要不可欠なハイパーパラメーターをいくつか用意した｡
And the reason this is so important is that you're going to be doing some hyperparameter optimization
これがとても重要な理由は､ ハイパーパラメーターの最適化を自分で行うことになるからだ｡
The fancy word for for trial and error.
試行錯誤を意味する洒落た言葉だ｡
And you need to understand the context of what it is that you're playing with.
そして､ 自分がプレーしていることの背景を理解する必要がある｡
And this is really the opportunity to build something that can beat other models.
そしてこれは､ 他のモデルに勝てるものを作るチャンスでもある｡
It's about understanding what kind of levers you've got to experiment with.
どのようなレバーを使って実験するのかを理解することだ｡
That is at the heart of the R&amp;D behind building leading models.
それが､ トップモデルを作るための研究開発の核心である｡
So we've got some hyperparameters to talk about.
そこで､ ハイパーパラメーターについて説明しよう｡
And then we're going to set up a supervised fine tuning trainer, an SFT.
そして､ 監督付きの微調整トレーナー､ SFTをセットアップする｡
Trainer, which is the sort of core object behind running this training.
トレーナーというのは､ このトレーニングの中核をなす存在だ｡
Um, looking at parts of the TRL library from Hugging Face and then we will kick off.
ハギング・フェイスからTRLライブラリーの一部を見て､ それからキックオフだ｡
Our own proprietary LM training process.
独自のLMトレーニングプロセス
It's going to be great.
素晴らしいものになるよ｡
So first of all, though, before we get to the great stuff, we do need to talk about some of the essential
というわけで､ まずは素晴らしい話に入る前に､ このプロセスをコントロールする重要なハイパーパラメーターについて､
hyperparameters that control this process, starting with Q Laura, and most of this is stuff that you're
Qローラから話をする必要がある｡
So the first hyperparameter I'll mention is one more time to bring up the target modules.
そこで最初に挙げるハイパーパラメーターは､ ターゲット・モジュールを呼び出すためのものだ｡
And I think you now remember exactly what this is.
そして､ これが何なのか､ 正確に覚えていただけたと思う｡
If you have an architecture of a transformer, a base model like Lama 3.1, it's way too big to try
トランスフォーマーのアーキテクチャがあれば､ ラマ3のようなベースモデルがある｡  1､ この巨大で偉大な建築物を微調整しようとするには､
and fine tune this enormous, great architecture.
あまりにも大きすぎる｡
So instead we pick a few layers in the architecture and we call those layers.
だから､ その代わりにアーキテクチャー内のいくつかのレイヤーを選び､ それをレイヤーと呼ぶ｡
The target modules are the ones we're going to target.
ターゲット・モジュールとは､ これからターゲットにするモジュールのことだ｡
We freeze everything.
何でも冷凍するんだ｡
We're not going to try and optimize these weights.
ウエイトを最適化するつもりはない｡
There's too many of them.
数が多すぎるんだ｡
Even in these target modules.
これらのターゲット・モジュールでもだ｡
We're not going to train these.
これをトレーニングするつもりはない｡
Rather, we're going to have onto one side a lower dimensional matrix that we will train this lower
そうではなく､ 低次元の行列を片側に持ってきて､ この低次元の行列を訓練し､
dimensional matrix and we will apply it to this original target module.
それを元のターゲット・モジュールに適用するのだ｡
We'll apply it in fact by multiplying them together, using that as a, as a as a delta on the weights
それを掛け合わせ､ ウェイトのデルタとして使うのだ｡
Um, and so we train these little guys and we apply them to the target modules, selected layers in
そうして､ この小人を訓練して､ ターゲット・モジュールに適用するんだ｡ ターゲット・モジュールとは､ 大きなアーキテクチャーの中で選択されたレイヤーのことだ｡
And then ah, uh, with this greater 3D goggles as the, as the logo, as the icon.
そして､ この大きな3Dゴーグルをロゴとして､ アイコンとして使っている｡
Uh, R is how many dimensions do we have in this lower dimensional, uh, adapter matrix?
Rは､ この低次元のアダプターマトリックスの次元数を表している｡
Uh, it's often common with learning with language learning tasks to start with eight.
ええと､ 言語学習の課題では､ 8から始めるのが一般的です｡
Um, for this project you're going to see I've got 32 as the R, because we've got so much training
このプロジェクトでは､ Rを32にしました｡ 学習データがたくさんあるので､ かなりの数のパラメータを使って学習できると考えたからです｡
But if that's running out of memory for you, you can you can have eight.
しかし､ もしそれでメモリが足りなくなるようなら､ 8枚にすることもできる｡
I actually I should say that the difference between 8 and 16 and 32 was quite marginal.
実際には､ 8と16と32の差はごくわずかだったと言うべきだろう｡
It did improve things, but not by a huge amount.
確かに改善されたが､ それほど大きな改善ではない｡
So if you have any memory problems, then stick with an R of eight.
記憶力に問題がある場合は､ Rを8にしてください｡
If you're on a smaller box that will be just fine.
もし､ あなたが小さい箱を使っているなら､ それで十分だ｡
32 is splashing out a bit, but but but it was worth it given the amount of training data we have.
32ドルというのは少々高いが､ トレーニングデータの量を考えれば､ それだけの価値はある｡
Alpha, you may remember, is the scaling factor.
アルファはスケーリング・ファクターである｡
It's used to multiply up the importance of this adapter when it's applied to the target module.
このアダプターをターゲット・モジュールに適用する際に､ その重要性を倍増させるために使用される｡
In fact, you may remember there are actually two Laura matrices.
実は､ ラウラのマトリックスは2つあることを覚えているだろうか｡
One is called Laura A and one is called Laura B, and the formula is that the change in weights is actually,
ひとつはローラA､ もうひとつはローラBと呼ばれ､ 計算式では重さの変化はアルファ値になる｡
The scaling factor times A times B, as simple as that.
スケーリングファクターにA×Bをかけたもの｡
That is that's the most maths that we're going to get in this course.
それが､ このコースで習う数学の一番多いところだ｡
And I think that's not not taking it too far.
そして､ それは行き過ぎではないと思う｡
So that's as simple as what alpha is.
アルファとはそういうものだ｡
It's the scaling factor.
スケーリングファクターだ｡
And the rule of thumb is to have alpha to be double R.
そして経験則では､ アルファはダブルRであるべきだ｡
That's what everyone does.
それは誰もがやっていることだ｡
By all means you can experiment with other values of alpha.
ぜひ他のアルファ値を試してみてほしい｡
But but the norm is is to do alpha is two r.
しかし､ しかし､ アルファは2Rでやるのが普通だ｡
So we're going to start with an R of 32 and an alpha of 64.
そこで､ まずRを32､ アルファを64とする｡
Quantisation of course is just what we call it when we reduce the precision of the weights in the base
定量化とはもちろん､ ベースモデルの重みの精度を下げることを指す｡
The base model has 32 bit numbers.
ベースモデルは32ビット｡
In it.
その中にある｡
We reduce it down to eight bits or even down to four bits, which sounds insane.
私たちはそれを8ビット､ あるいは4ビットにまで減らす｡
We did that with our base model and we saw that we were still getting results.
ベースモデルでそれをやってみたところ､ やはり結果が出た｡
They weren't great results, but I think that would be true for the base model overall.
素晴らしい結果ではなかったが､ ベースモデル全体に言えることだと思う｡
And we did see actually that the eight bit model did better than the four bit model, but they were
実際､ 8ビットモデルは4ビットモデルよりも成績が良かったが､
both pretty miserable at it.
どちらもかなり惨めだった｡
And by all means you can try training with the eight bit model too.
そしてぜひ､ 8ビットモデルでのトレーニングも試してみてほしい｡
But we're going to train with a four bit model because that's what will fit in in our in our memory.
しかし､ 4ビットのモデルでトレーニングすることにした｡
And that's, uh, but I'd be interested if you try the eight bit to see whether you get significantly
でも､ 8ビットを試してみて､ 有意に異なる結果が得られるかどうか､
different results.
興味があるね｡
And then the final hyperparameter is a new one that we've not talked about before, except to show you
そして最後のハイパーパラメーターは､ コード・ドロップアウトでお見せする以外､ これまでお話ししたことのない新しいものです｡
So dropout is a type.
つまり､ ドロップアウトはタイプなのだ｡
It's a technique that's known as a regularization technique, of which there are a few, um, which
正則化テクニックとして知られているテクニックで､ いくつかありますが､ つまり､
means that it's a technique designed to prevent the model from doing what's known as overfitting.
モデルがいわゆるオーバーフィッティングをしないように設計されたテクニックです｡
And overfitting is when a model gets so much training data, it goes through so much training that it
オーバーフィッティングとは､ モデルがあまりにも多くの訓練データを取得し､ あまりにも多くの訓練を経て､
starts to just expect exactly the structure of the data in the training data set, and then give back
訓練データセットに含まれるデータの構造を正確に予想し､ その通りの答えを返すようになることである｡
And it starts to to no longer understand the general trends of what's being suggested, but instead
そして､ もはや提案されていることの一般的な傾向を理解するのではなく､
it sort of hones in on precisely those words and the prediction that comes later.
その言葉やその後に来る予測に集中するようになる｡
And as a result of that, if you give it some new point that it hasn't seen in its training data set,
その結果､ トレーニングデータセットで見たことのないような新しいポイントを与えると､ 一般的なテーマを学習しているのではなく､
it performs really badly because it's not being learning the general themes, it's being learning to.
そのテーマに合わせて学習しているため､ 成績は非常に悪くなる｡
It's been too much learning the very specifics of this training data set.
このトレーニングデータセットの特殊性を学ぶのは大変だった｡
I'm being a bit hand-wavy again, but hopefully you get the idea.
また少し手探り状態になってしまったが､ ご理解いただけただろうか｡
That's called overfitting when you are too precisely adhering to the training data set and the outcome.
訓練データセットと結果に正確に準拠しすぎることをオーバーフィッティングと呼ぶ｡
And it's not learning the general flavor of what's of what it's trying to predict.
そして､ 何を予測しようとしているのかの一般的な風味を学んでいない｡
Um, and it's that flavor.
あの､ あの味です｡
It's that nuance of what's going on.
そういうニュアンスなんだ｡
That's what you're trying to teach the model.
それをモデルに教えようとしているんだ｡
Um, so that's that's the sort of that's the preamble, the explanation of what?
ええと､ つまり､ それが前文であり､ 何の説明なんですか？
Of what overfitting is.
オーバーフィッティングとは何か？
But now, to tell you exactly what dropout does, and it's really simple, what dropout actually does,
しかし今､ ドロップアウトが何をするのかを正確にお伝えすると､ 実に単純なことなのだが､
uh, is it quite simply removes a random subset of the neurons from the deep neural network.
ドロップアウトが実際にすることは､ ディープ・ニューラル・ネットワークからニューロンのランダムなサブセットを削除することだ｡
From the transformer, it takes a random percentage.
変圧器からはランダムなパーセンテージを取る｡
We're going to start with 10%, takes 10% of the neurons, and it just wipes them out, sets the activations
まず10％から始め､ ニューロンの10％を取り出し､ それらを消去して活性をゼロにし､
to zero so that they are not involved in the forward pass or the backward pass.
前進パスにも後退パスにも関与しないようにする｡
They're not involved in predicting the next token and they're not involved in optimizing.
彼らは次のトークンの予測には関与しないし､ 最適化にも関与しない｡
It's as if they're just not there.
まるでそこにいないかのようだ｡
And as a result, every time that you're going through training, the model is seeing a different subset,
その結果､ トレーニングのたびに､ モデルは異なるサブセット､ 異なる90％のニューラルネットワークを見ることになる｡
And so the, the, the weights are sort of discouraged from being too precise and to and looking too
そのため､ 重みは､ 1セットの入力トークンを正確に探しすぎることを抑制し､ その代わりに､
precisely for one set of input tokens, but instead, because different neurons participate every time
異なるニューロンがトレーニング・プロセスに毎回参加することで､
in the training process, it starts to learn more.
より多くのことを学び始める｡
The general theme than learning very specifically how to expect different tokens.
一般的なテーマは､ さまざまなトークンを期待する方法を具体的に学ぶことだ｡
So it prevents any one neuron from becoming too specialized.
つまり､ 1つのニューロンが専門化しすぎるのを防いでいるのだ｡
It supports this concept of more general understanding in the neural network, in this very simplistic
これは､ ニューロンの10％をプロセスから取り除くという非常に単純化された方法で､
way of just removing 10% of the neurons from the process, a different 10% each time.
神経回路網におけるより一般的な理解という概念をサポートするものである｡
So that's dropout.
それがドロップアウトだ｡
It's really very simple.
とてもシンプルなことなんだ｡
When you realize it, it's literally dropping out a bunch of the neurons and the the norm.
それに気づいたとき､ それは文字通り､ ニューロンと規範の束を取り除くことなのだ｡
It's usually somewhere in the in the range of 5% through to 20%.
通常は5％から20％の範囲だ｡
Um, I've picked 10% as the dropout that we're using.
ええと､ 10％をドロップアウトとして使っています｡
You should absolutely experiment with 5% and 20% and see whether you get better results or not.
5％や20％で実験し､ より良い結果が得られるかどうかを確かめるべきだ｡
It is very much a hyperparameter to be experimented with.
これは非常に実験的なハイパーパラメーターである｡
Okay, so those are the five hyperparameters for Q.
さて､ これがQの5つのハイパーパラメータだ｡
Laura, next time we'll talk about five hyperparameters for the overall training process.
ローラ､ 次回は全体的なトレーニングプロセスに関する5つのハイパーパラメータについて話そう｡